Guide to the T. Burns Collection of Racial Stereotypes, 1880s-1983 RL.10191
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
T. Burns collection of racial stereotypes
1880s-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Burns, T. "Thomas" (collector)
RL.10191
7 Linear Feet
Collection includes advertisements, games, sheet music, serial illustrations, and other caricatures of African Americans predominately dating from the late 1800s through the mid-1900s.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Historical note
T. Burns was an African American collector who began acquiring this material in the late 1980s.
Provenance
The T. Burns Collection of Racial Stereotypes was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in December 2014.
Collection Overview
Collection includes advertisements, games, sheet music, serial illustrations, and other caricatures of African Americans predominately dating from the late 1800s through the mid-1900s. A significant portion of the illustrations were excerpted from news or literature magazines such as Harper's Weekly, Frank Leslie's Popular Magazine, and Puck magazine. The collection also includes advertisements from companies, including Aunt Jemima and Cream of Wheat, which appeared in women's magazines such as Modern Priscilla and Needlecraft. Many items depict African Americans in rural or Southern settings. Of note in the collection are a set of shackles, which have no known provenance or date, but which appear to have been intended for slaves (or could be a reproduction from a later time period).
Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Stereotypes (Social psychology) in advertising; Race discrimination -- United States; Racism -- United States; Advertising -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Cream of Wheat Corporation (Minneapolis, Minn.); Jemima, Aunt.
- T. Burns collection of racial stereotypes
  - Boarding House Blues poster, undated (Box 1)
  - Aunt Jemima advertisements, 1917-1953 (Box 1)
  - Aunt Jemima's packaging materials, undated (Box 1)
  - Aunt Jemina's promotional materials, undated (Box 1)
  - Barker's advertisements, 1890 (Box 1)
  - Cream of Wheat promotional materials, undated (Box 2)
  - Cream of Wheat advertisements in Needlecraft magazine, 1916-1925; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Cream of Wheat advertisements in The Housewife magazine, 1914-1916 (Box 2)
  - Cream of Wheat advertisements in The Modern Priscilla magazine, 1913 (Box 2)
  - Cream of Wheat advertisements, loose (Box 2, Box 7)
  - Gold Dust advertisements, 1895-1905 (Box 2)
  - Sheet music, 1897-1944; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Illustrations from serial publications, titles unknown, 1862-1933 (Box 1)
  - Illustrations from Puck, 1890 (Box 1)
  - Illustrations from Harper's Weekly, 1869-1922 (Box 1)
  - Illustrations from Frank Leslie's Popular Monthly, 1862-1885 (Box 1)
  - Photomechanical prints, loose, 1873 and 1904 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous advertisements and artwork, 1908-1938 (Box 3, Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes print ads for Winchester rifles, F.B. & C Kid, and Bemis cotton bags. Also includes a decorative placemat.
  - Topsy advertisement, mounted on glass, undated (Box 7)
  - Old Virginny brand charcoal bag, undated (Box 3)
  - Leahey's Heatless Trouser Press, 1914 (Box 3)
  - Southern Cook Book: 322 Old Dixie Recipes, 1939 (Box 4)
  - John Henry: Steel-Drivin' Man, 1966 (Box 4)
  - The All About Story Book, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Little Brown Koko, 1940 (Box 4)
  - The Children's Own Readers: Book Two, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Little Black Sambo, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Fat Albert and the Cosby Kids: Getting It Together, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Make-Me-Jig Puzzle: Beautiful Venice, undated (Box 4)
  - Make-Me-Jig Puzzle: Shooting the Rapids, undated (Box 4)
  - Snake Eyes boxed game, undated (Box 4)
  - Weekly Picture Puzzle: The Ole Kentucky Home, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Various playing card decks, undated (Box 4)
  - Super Paint Book, undated (Box 4)
  - Funeral programs, 1940, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Conference proceedings, 1934, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Zulu Lulu drink swizzle sticks, undated (Box 5)
  - Piccaninny menus (2), undated (Box 5)
  - Darkie Toothpaste puppet, undated (Box 5)
  - Shackles, undated (Box 6)
    A set of iron shackles, with some rust, with no accompanying documentation or provenance. They appear to have been intended for slaves (or could be a reproduction from a later time period).